Guide to the G. Rosimov (Iurii of Rosimov) Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
G. Rosimov (I︠U︡riĭ Ofrosimov) papers
1923-1967
GEN MSS 312
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.4
(7 boxes)
Writings by Rosimov, including poetry, literary essays and children's stories. Correspondence with Russian émigré writers and cultural figures, mainly on personal and literary matters.
Other formats include 1 broadside
Rosimov, G.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Aleksis Rannit, 1971.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
G. ROSIMOV
G. Rosimov was born IUrii Viktorovich Ofrosimov in Moscow in 1894. After participating in the Civil War on the side of the Whites, in 1920 Rosimov settled in Berlin, where he became known as a theater critic, poet and participant in Russian émigré life. It was at this time that he met many of the correspondents represented in his papers, such as Roman Gul' (his editor at the newspaper Rul' ), Ivan Il'in and Vladas Stanka (as a member of Stanka's political group "Mir i trud"). In 1923, he published a collection of poetry Stikhi ob uteriannom, which was followed in 1926 by Teatr, a book of critical essays. Rosimov's critical articles were invariably published under his real name, IU. Ofrosimov (or his initials, IU. O.). His publications as IU. Ofrosimov include the 1926 collection Teatr. Fel'etony, and later articles in Novoe russkoe slovo (see Box 7, folder 134) and Novyi zhurnal (see Box 6, folders 125, 126-128).
In 1933, Rosimov moved to Belgrade, where he apparently was arrested by German forces during the Second World War. He spent some time in prison camps, and then in displaced persons' camps, where he befriended a new group of Russian writers. After the war, Rosimov married Dorothea Vogels and settled in the small town of Ennenda near Glarus in Switzerland, and later in Lugano. In later years Rosimov continued to write for émigré publications. He died in Palermo, Sicily, on October 19, 1967, and is buried in Lugano.
Scope and Contents
Series I. Correspondence includes letters to Rosimov, mainly from Russian émigré writers. Principal correspondents include: Lidiia Alekseeva, E. F. Danchakov, Ivan Elagin, Roman Gul', Sergei and Natal'ia IAblonovskii, Ivan Il'in, Dmitrii Klenovskii, N. Z. Rybinskii, Vladas Stanka, S. Starova, and Aleksei Petrovich Struve. Although the dates of the correspondence range from 1939 to 1968, the bulk of the letters dates from two periods: immediately after the war (1945-1952), and the last decade of his life (1958-1968).
Series II. Writings consists primarily of holograph manuscripts of a number of stories for children by Rosimov. A significant number of his poems, a few articles and two plays are also included.
Children's literature, Russian -- 20th Century; Russian literature -- 20th Century; Russia -- Emigration and immigration; Alekseeva, Lidii︠a︡, 1909-1989; Ansteĭ, Olʹga, 1912-1985; Elagin, Ivan, 1918-1987; Gulʹ, Roman, 1896-1986; Ilʹin, I. A. (Ivan Aleksandrovich), 1883-1954; Klenovskiĭ, Dmitriĭ I., 1892-1976; Rosimov, G.; Stanka, Vladas, 1884-1968
- Correspondence, 1949-52; Series I
  - Alekseeva, Lidiia, 1949-52 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Scope and Contents
    Pseudonym of L. A. Ivannikova
  - Danchakov, E. F., 1953-65, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3-12)
    Includes photograph of addressee
  - Davats, Viktor, 1946 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Elagin, Ivan Venediktovich Anstei, Ol'ga Nikolaevna, 1947-49, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    I. V. Elagin pseudonym of I. V. Matveev
    O. N. Anstei signed as Ol'ga Matveeva
    Includes signed typescript of poem
    by Ivan Elagin
  - Goldenweiser, Alexis, 1950 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gornyi, Sergei, 1946-47 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Grebenshchikov, Igor, 1948-52 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    Includes photographs and poems
  - Grossen, Leo, 1951 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gul', Roman Borisovich, 1946-53,n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20-24)
  - Hentschel, Herbert, 1948 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - IAblonovskaia, Natal'ia IAblonovskii, Sergei Viktorovich, 1946-68, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26-37)
    Includes clippings, TLS from Aleksei
    Struve, and TLS from P. Shostak
  - IAkovlev, A., 1948 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Il'in, Ivan Aleksandrovich, 1946-51, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39-41)
  - Karpikhina, Aleksandra Georgievna, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Klenovskii, Dmitrii, 1950-65 (Box 3, Folder 43-54)
    Pseudonym of Dmitrii Iosifovich
    Krachkovskii
  - Luszek, Annaliese, 1947-48 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    With notes from F. Peltzer
  - Nemolin, B. N., 1947 Aug 12 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Peltzer, Friedrich Peltzer, E., 1947-48 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    Also spelled (Fedor) Pel'ttser
    With notes from A. Luszek
  - Rabchinskaia, IUliia, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Rybinskii, Nikolai Zakharovich Rybinskaia, Anna, 1946-50 (Box 4, Folder 59-68)
    Includes correspondence with O. Fromm
    and B. Riabukhin
    Includes programs to cultural events
    at Displaced-Persons Camps
  - Rybinskii, Nikolai Zakharovich Rybinskaia, Anna, 1951-55, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 69-73)
  - Shifman [?], Ol'ga, 1939 Jun 20 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Stanka, Vladas, 1947-67 (Box 5, Folder 75-80)
    Also known as: Vladimir Stankevich
    Includes notes from R. B. Gul'
  - Starova, S., 1949-53 (Box 5, Folder 81-82)
    Includes notices re "Pereklichka"
  - Strandman, B. de, 1946-48 (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Struve, Aleksei Petrovich, 1947-53, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 84-86)
  - Tauber, E. (Box 5, Folder 87)
    Includes notice re "Pereklichka"
  - Unidentified, 1948-50 (Box 5, Folder 88)
- Writings, Series II
  - WORKS FOR CHILDREN
    - "Bobkina villa": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - "Boltlivaia cherepakha": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - "Chempiony": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - "Dressirovannyi pes": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - "Dva bashmaka": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - "Fyrka": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - "Gigant": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - "Glupoe leto": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - "Ia i moia pechka": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - "Istoriia s ezhami": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - "Khrabrye Georginy": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - "O byvshem 'Geroe'": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - "O chem dver' skripela": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 101)
    - "Otchego zvezdy noch'iu": holograph, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - "Paskhal'naia istoriia": holograph, incomplete, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - "Pochemu koshki murlykaiut": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - "Radio-istoriia": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - "Sbezhavshee moloko": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - "Skazka o minuvshei zime": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - "Sladie i gor'kie": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - "Sobach'ia zhizn'": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - "Soroki": holograph, signed "Chika Buka", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - "Strannaia istoriia"
      - Holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 111)
      - Holograph, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - "Umnye nozhnitsy": holograph, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - "Vozvrashchenie ryzhego kota": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - "Vseznaika": holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - Untitled: incomplete holograph, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Untitled: holograph, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - Untitled: holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - Untitled: holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - Untitled: holograph, signed "Chika Bura", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 120)
    - Untitled: holograph, n.d (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - Untitled: holograph, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - Untitled: holograph, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    - Poems, holograph (poetry), 1923-47, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 124)
    - "Pamiati poeta": offprint of article re V. Korvin-Piotrovskii, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - "Rifmovannye dogadki: o poezii D. Klenovskogo" (article)
      - Offprint, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 126)
      - Typescript, annotated and corrected (Box 6, Folder 127)
      - Typescript, signed, annotated by G. Rosimov and Roman Gul' (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - "Svinopies [?]: skazka v 3 aktakh po Andersenu G. Rosimova": holograph, corrected (play) (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - "Svinopies [?]": holograph fragment (play), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - Untitled holograph of article, re V. IA. Iretskii and Russian Berlin (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - Untitled play (based on A. S. Griboedov's Gore ot uma ): holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 132-133)
    - Scrapbook of clippings: from Novoe russkoe slovo, 1953-67
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Oversize, Box 7, folder 134
- Oversize, 1953-67
  - Scrapbook of clippings: from Novoe russkoe slovo, 1953-67 (Box 7, Folder 134)